does trt cause gyno or maybe we should
ask can it cause
gyno okay so welcome back to the trt and
hormone optimization YouTube channel and
back with us as a guest is Gil T welcome
back Gil thank you Stephen I really
appreciate it as always welcome back
today let's talk about gyo the typical
question in the YouTube search bar is
does trt cause gyno or maybe we should
ask can it cause
gyno Okay so first we have to understand
what gynecomastia is so let's preface
this by saying that gynecomastia is the
development of breast tissue in males
and it is often unwanted and there are a
number of reasons why this can occur so
before we can treat any condition right
we first have to diagnose it so the
diagnosis for gynecomastia is not
something that you can do at home it is
not the sensitivity around your nipples
it is not an increase in what you
perceived to be breast tissue or an
increase necessarily in in the size of
your chest or the softness of your chest
these are things that need to be
diagnosed clinically oftentimes guys
have a little too much fat around their
chest area and they misconstrue this for
gynecomastia when in fact it is not so
it is very important to distinguish uh
with that said uh one of the studies
that I'm going to reference and there
are three that I've looked at recently
one of them uh actually stated a
statistic which I found quite
interesting that up to 30% of males at
some point in their life are going to be
affected uh from gynecomastia 30% three
out of 10 men and it went on to uh refer
to the prevalence of gynea being most
prominent AC uh around three different
times of your life one is immediately
after birth while there are still high
levels of female hormones circulating
from the mother the time as we've known
uh to be true is during puberty when the
hormonal milu of a male is off balance
and that's usually when they break out
in acne and have significant changes and
then the third time which I found
interesting although not surprising is
during old age and one of the studies
goes specifically into detail why this
is relevant because what we know about
men as they age is they generally become
hypo gonadal and suffer low testosterone
so let's refer to the first study which
I will pull up a a figure to
explain
specifically what goes on during
gynecomastia okay so if we look at
this image here on the screen and this
here is from a study from last year from
2023 this is the soff study uh Which is
less than
which is responsible for the AOL areolar
development around the nipples and then
prolactin as we know is a prol lactating
hormone which is responsible for the
formation of breast milk so all four of
these must be present in order for
proper breast
development there's a fifth aspect which
is not referred to in the study but I've
harped on this many times over the years
which is a genetic predisposition right
hormones are different in the way they
affect different people genetic
predisposition is essentially very
important you can have someone who is
more sensitive to these aspects you can
have someone who is unaffected by these
aspects but what's interesting here is
if we go down to the bottom of the
screen and you look at the testosterone
and right below it says inhibitory
action on breast tissue what does this
mean it means that a proper Androgen
level in and of itself free testosterone
is protective of this environment that
we see to the north of this model which
means that when you have optimal tea
levels these other hormones require even
more of them in order to overpower the
testosterone and this is interesting
because we know from the bodybuilding
World generally guys do not develop
gynecomastia while they're on their
Cycles but as they're coming off their
cycle there is a perfect storm if you
will where Androgen levels are low shbg
tends to rise up therefore binding on
more of the free testosterone and that
is secondary to serm use like
different mechanisms of gynecomastia and
essentially the the number of men that
are affected now this third study is
extremely interesting because it does
touch on a couple other points that I
think a lot of people uh would realize
uh that they're probably affected by so
this study was done by the University of
Milan the Urological department and this
is a 2021 study now this is a
metaanalysis of 32 different studies
that were collected and it talks about
the pharmacological or drug induced
gynecomastia and I think a lot of people
would find it
interesting that spirolactone or
aldactone which is a frequently
prescribed diuretic we know we use it in
uh in females with PCOS specifically to
block the Androgen receptor activity uh
it is known to be an an
anti-androgen uh and in fact it
increases the prevalence of gomasa in
men who are on spirin actone and the
reason for that is again the protective
nature of
androgens uh is then inhibited and then
the other hormones that we discussed
earlier have an opportunity overcome
that environment and start the process
the other one is finasteride which a lot
of guys are obviously familiar with as
well it is a DHT blocker or a five Alpha
reductase inhibitor uh and that is
another one that is mentioned in this
study for those that do wish to look a
little
deeper at the uh at these studies the
links are going to be down below in the
description uh but this is a fairly uh
fairly new study from um 2021 as well so
you have to uh you have to understand
that gynecomastia is not as uncommon as
people may think but it is also very
preventable if you understand that it is
not estrogen that is causing it is a
combination of low androgens low
androgens is not just your total
testosterone low free androgens can be
an elevation of shbg which then binds
free testosterone allowing prolactin
igf1 progesterone and some circulating
estrogen which again is only responsible
for the ductal portion um to overpower
the Androgen effect so usually what I
find in guys who do have genuine
gynecomastia is a number of factors in
common number one they usually were
affected by this condition during
puberty at some point or they've already
been diagnosed and potentially treated
via surgery to remove the gland however
some of the gland was Left Behind these
people have already proven to be more
susceptible and then third we often find
elevated prolactin levels elevated
progestin levels and usually it's a
result of previous um anabolic steroid
abuse and then generally we will find
high shbg and some of the older guys
which leads to low free testosterone or
they're simply suppressed or they're
just hypogonadal and untreated very
rarely if at all I I honestly can't
think of a situation where I found a man
unproperly administered and properly
managed testosterone replacement therapy
who's presented with actual gyesa as I
said earlier it is usually just their
manifestation in their head where they
think well this is gyno because my
nipples are a little sensitive or I have
a little fatty tissue around the breast
area and and very seldomly is that truly
diagnoses gynecomastia so there's a lot
of misconceptions and estrogen as as
always always gets the blame people
think they need an aromatase inhibitor
in order to reduce the risk of gcity and
that is simply just not the case so if
older man with gomasa on
trt don't he Improvement after a while
on the proper protocol uh what do they
do certain um treatments older men
generally don't really present with this
if they've never had it before but if
they do once they're on trt which is
very uncommon because remember as the
study suggested in older men it is
usually a result of low testosterone
which is inhibitory of gyc mtia but if
they do it's likely an igf1 SL genetic
predisposition prolactin issue and
they're probably on some sort of a DHT
inhibitor like feride or dester from the
urologist whether it's to treat BPH or
if they are concerned about hair loss so
usually again they're blocking the
mechanism of the prot protective action
of androgens I've personally never
experienced it because none of our
patients are any of these
medications you mentioned um sensitive
nipples is that something that is
typical or um temporary starting trt
yeah so both it is extremely common when
starting testosterone and in fact so
much so that we warn patients in advance
otherwise we know we're going to get a
call in a couple of weeks saying I've
have gynecomastia but in essence when
you do begin testosterone replacement
you are going to have a an initial spike
in androgen you're going to have some
delayed response in metabolites and your
entire hormone homeostatic state is
going to need to adjust for a matter of
a couple of months before that subsides
so very common to feel a different
sensation in sensitive areas that are
known to be sensitive to hormonal
fluctuation such as the nipples uh so it
is very common and yes it generally will
subside in 95% of patients and when it
doesn't then we just have a physical
assessment but like I said I've never
seen true gyas is a result of properly
administered torte unless there were
ancillaries or other conditions
involved okay thank you so much Gil for
clearing this out my pleasure thank
you